Chapter 83 Jonah historically regarded.
Reference was made to the historical story of Jonah and the whale in the
preceding chapter. Now some Nantucketers rather distrust this historical story of
Jonah and the whale. But then there were some skeptical Greeks and Romans who
standing out from the Orthodox pagans of their times equally doubted the story of
Hercules and the whale and Arion and the dolphin. And yet their doubting those
traditions did not make those traditions one wit the less facts for all that.
One old Sag Harbor whaleman's chief reason for questioning the Hebrew story
was this. He had one of those quaint old-fashioned Bibles embellished with
curious unscientific plates, one of which represented Jonah's whale with two
spouts in his head, a peculiarity only true with respect to a species of the
Leviathan, the right whale and varieties of that order, concerning which the
fishermen have this saying, a penny roll would choke him. His swallow is so very
small. But to this, Bishop Jeb's anticipative answer is ready. It is not
necessary, hence the bishop, that we consider Jonah as tombed in the whale's
belly, but is temporarily lodged in some part of his mouth. And this seems
reasonable enough in the good bishop.
For truly the right whale's mouth would accommodate a couple of wis tables, and
comfortably seat all the players.
Possibly too, Jonah might have enscconced himself in a hollow tooth,
but on second thoughts, the right whale is toothless.
Another reason which Sag Harbor, he went by that name, urged for his want of
faith in this matter of the prophet was something obscurely in reference to his
incarcerated body and the whales gastric juices. But this objection likewise
falls to the ground because a German exedigotist supposes that Jonah must
have taken refuge in the floating body of a dead whale even as the French
soldiers in the Russian campaign turned their dead horses into tents and crawled
into them. Besides, it has been divined by other continental commentators that
when Jonah was thrown overboard from the Japa ship, he straight away affected his
escape to another vessel nearby. Some vessel with a whale for a figure head,
and I would add, possibly called the whale, as some craft nowadays are
christened, the shark, the gull, the eagle. Nor have there been wanting
learned exotists who have appined that the whale mentioned in the book of Jonah
merely meant a life preserver, an inflated bag of wind which the
endangered prophet swam to, and so was saved from a watery doom. Poor Sag
Harbor therefore seems worsted all round. But he had still another reason
for his want of faith. It was this, if I remember right, Jonah was swallowed by
the whale in the Mediterranean Sea. And after 3 days, he was vomited up
somewhere within 3 days journey of Nineveh, a city on the Tigris, very much
more than 3 days journey across from the nearest point of the Mediterranean
coast. How is that? But was there no other way for the whale to land the
prophet within that short distance of Nineveh? Yes, he might have carried him
round by the way of the Cape of Good Hope, but not to speak of the passage
through the whole length of the Mediterranean and another passage up the
Persian Gulf in the Red Sea. Such a supposition would involve the complete
circumnavigation of all Africa in 3 days, not to speak of the Tigress waters
near the sight of Nineveh being too shallow for any whale to swim in.
Besides, this idea of Jonas's weathering the Cape of Good Hope at so early a day
would rest the honor of the discovery of that great headland from Bartholomew
Diaz, its reputed discoverer, and so make modern history a liar.
But all these foolish arguments of old Sag Harbor only evinced his foolish
pride of reason, a thing still more reprehensible in him, seeing that he had
but little learning except what he had picked up from the sun and the sea. I
say it only shows his foolish, impious pride and abominable devilish rebellion
against the reverend clergy. For by a Portuguese Catholic priest, this very
idea of Jonah's going to Nineveh via the Cape of Good Hope was advanced as a
signal magnification of the general miracle. And so it was. Besides, to this
day, the highly enlightened Turks devoutly believe in the historical story
of Jonah. And some three centuries ago, an English traveler in old Harris's
voyages speaks of a Turkish mosque built in honor of Jonah. In which mosque was a
miraculous lamp that burnt without any oil.